Beautiful evening and gracious breezes
that erase from the day
excessive and great heat
Blow even more calmly,
grant our wishes
Cheer our hearts
And sir, do we understand each other?
Yes sir, everything understood
There's no need to speak anymore
He leaves without saying goodbye...
Where could my beloved be?
I'm starting to suspect
Heaven conspires to my design
Beautiful prospect, I'm committed with good judgment to its triumph
Ah father, being such to me, you love me
Come on, tell me the rest for goodness sake
It's my time
It's my time and there's nothing more to be done
Ah father, Ah father
Speak I beg you
Now, my daughter, it's best to stay silent
Secret discussions dont always remain so
Do you understand, do you get my meaning?
I dare not speak
Now, my daughter, it's best to stay silent, I dare not speak
You get my meaning, I dare not speak
Truly, it would be a great incivility
to deprive you of comfort and freedom
Let's go, brother, let's go
Let's go sister, to dine for now
Each one keeps their agreement, everyone
We may see each other with the passing of time
We can happily converse among ourselves
Yes, daughter, in the end I've found you a husband
And when?
Now, the deal is concluded
With Nanni?
Oh, Nanni indeed! He can wipe that drool off his chin
This time, he won't get any
But...
There aren't many 'buts', my daughter, Nanni is poor
And I who am rich?
You will be
What does it matter if I'll be rich, if I won't be happy?
And why not?
Because I love him
You make me laugh. Now, you'll love this one
But how can one love another, when one turns from their beloved?
Easily, girls don't have a will of their own
But when it comes from within, what can be done?
One obeys and stays silent
But what should I do, if Nanni comes with such charm?
Turn your back to him, and walk away
When he comes to make love, you must always tell him no
Do you care for me?
No, sir
Sir, no
Do you want to marry me?
I know well what I'm doing
I'm your father,
and this is my wish
Beware of saying yes to him
Poor me! Poor Nanni!
How can I keep saying no to him when I always want to say yes?
He cares for me so much!
We've been bonded in love for so long,
and to leave him like this...
breaks my heart
Yet, I must obey and so perish
For Heaven's sake!
There he is; it might be better if I leave
Where are you going, Sandrina?
I don't even know myself
Are you perchance angry?
No!
But, you seem troubled
Your eyes are red
You look like you've been crying
Tell me, dear, what happened?
Nothing
But why won't you look at me?
Why won't you speak to me?
Because... no
What? What have I done?
I don't know...
Poor me! What does this mean?
Is it that you do not care for me anymore? That you share no more love for me?
(And yet I must say it) No, sir
What? Am I not the one you've loved until now, the one who loved you faithfully?
The one who was to marry you?
No, sir
You speak to me this way, and yet you cry?
Black soul! Deceitful, wicked girl, you wish for my downfall, you desire my death
You'll be pleased. I'll go drown myself in some ditch
or from some cliff, I'll go and break my neck
With such a thorn in my heart, I can't go on living
Ah no, sir!
But why do you hold me back? What do you care about me?
You don't send me away? Does this heart not betray me?
You won't leave me, cruel one?
No, sir
I'm going mad. Who taught you such an air?
(Truly, it's better if I go away.)
You're leaving?
No
Are you driving me away? Should I leave you?
Are you disgusted?
No
Cursed 'no'!
(I'm desperate.)
But speak, but talk, finally decide
Do you love me or not? Should I leave or stay?
Am I to be your husband or not?
What a tangled web this is!
What do you want me to say? What do you want me to do?
My hostile father scolds and threatens me if I speak of loving you, if I say yes
He commands and tells me he found a husband, that I mustn't oppose, that it's a better match
I must leave you; I can't speak to you
I mustn't oppose
No, I mustn't...
What a tangled web this is!
I must leave you; I can't speak to you
And I'm dying of distress. Is this enough for you?
Now I understand what is going on
That baboon, that raging old sorcerer, has orchestrated this farce at my expense
But I'll see for myself. I want to know who dares to take the bread from my mouth
Sandra is mine. Without her, I couldn't live
Poor Nanni!
It's been more than three years that I've been courting her
Every day, I bring her fruits or a small bouquet
And every night, I serenade her under her window with my little guitar
Is another dandy, who besides is unknown to me,
coming to mess up my plans?
I want to go to her father, I want to know who he is
I want him to tell me everything, from A to Z
And once he's revealed the whole mystery to me, one of us is bound for the cemetery
There's no remedy, no compensation
I feel a gnawing when I think of it
I'm all bile, all poison
My insides burn, my chest is on fire
Before losing her, I'd rather die
That old coot, that sorcerer,
who is nothing but bones and skin,
will regret it, and will swing for it
Here's my dinner ready: spring water, a bit of salad, and Moroccan bread
It's a meal fit for a king
But kings don't have to make their meals tasty
the salsa of fasting and labor
Goodness! It's already night,
and Nencio hasn't come yet
I wouldn't want the devil to stick in his hoof and lead him astray
He hasn't shown up all day
Tonight, I noticed him all troubled and flustered, responding with stammers, and grimacing
Why am I so poor?
Why is he rich and has some stake under the sun?
Everyone envies me, everyone wants him
If he had nothing, I'd have no rivals, and I'd be happier
But I hear someone. Here he is
Ah, it's not him...
It's my Nanni, returning distraught and weary
What the devil is happening?
I'm desperate
I have a demon in my hair
I want to jump off a cliff
Speak. What is it, brother?
Ah, you make me tremble!
What has happened?
Speak, what is it, brother?
N: I'm ruined
V: How? Why?
My Sandrina is not for me
Who has slighted you such?
Your Nencio is taking her from me
My Nencio? Really?
Oh what anger, oh what torment!
I feel my heart pounding,
It cannot end like this
And where is that traitor?
With Sandrina, making love
With Sandrina? Speak, speak!
That traitor...
Ah, you make me tremble
Hurry, hurry, hurry,
let's go find them
I want to tear out his heart,
I want to gut him
[Applause]
[Music]
What will you do with so much clothes on,
It looks like you've raided a Haberdashery?
Oh brother, last night I did not act as you did,
who made such a ruckus,
And then slept soundly like a rock
I haven't slept a wink
And before dawn, I wandered hither and thither,
and have made it so that, unless the devil intervenes,
I hope to thwart the wedding
Well, you know, the early bird catches the worm
Anyway, you're a remarkable woman if you succeed
Do you think Filippa might recognize me?
Not in the slightest
Does this fit me well?
Enchantingly, in these clothes you look just like an eighty-year-old woman
And with the other outfit?
In that one, well...
Trying to turn a woman into a man seems a bit ridiculous to me,
And you might lack some... appendages
Quiet, I hear people. It's time
Be careful. Retreat!
Right Away
Now for the moment of truth
Hurry up
I'm coming, where are we going?
To the judge to file a complaint against that scoundrel Nanni
Oh, dear father...
All aflutter, you'll soon see,
that if the notary wishes to examine me,
I'll start shaking like a leaf
Shake, quiver, crumble,
You've got to go
Pray, sir, may I inquire,
is a certain Nencio the lout residing here?
No, sister
Alas, just my luck!
I must have taken the wrong path
I've been walking for four hours, sir,
searching, asking, inquiring, questioning, and I can't find him...
I believe I've traversed the whole plain
I'll show you the way; he's not far
Ah, so weary, and at this age,
unfortunately, it will be far the same
There it is
May heaven reward you
Oh brother, you're a lifesaver
If you only knew the trouble I'm in because of that man...
"But, one must swallow and remain silent" says the proverb
and "those without judgment better have good legs."
What business do you have with him?
Of that I can't speak, I must remain silent and bite my tongue
S: Poor soul!
F: (She piques my curiosity greatly.)
You can speak freely with me
(That is the husband)
What do you say?!
Oh, nothing
"Once spoken, words don’t return to the mouth," says the proverb
"and he who doesn’t know how to stay silent doesn’t know how to live," I know
I'm not a gossip, except of good recipes!
But those with great troubles, make a loud cry
Speak on, there's no risk in venting to me
I tear up when I think of it
Poor dear daughter!
Poor creatures!
You still have, from what I see, a daughter:
May heaven preserve her for you
She is tall and beautiful, modest, and domestic
Open your eyes, poor wretched woman
Don't drown here like I have done
She was just like you, my dear girl,
Wise and beautiful, and throughout the neighborhood
everyone marvelled at her so much, it was pure joy
"As long as you have teeth in your mouth, you don't know what's in store for you,"
says the proverb
"Those who do nothing make no mistakes, but the truth always floats to the surface,"
And what happened to her?
This Nencio, on Carnival, came to Peregola
He saw her and became infatuated
Everyone said he was such a good match
and the girl let herself be charmed
The fire ignited, and the devil fiercely fanned the flames,
that they secretly wed in haste
(Nencio married! Oh, the rascal!)
For a while, he played the good husband
Gradually, he grew distant, until he completely pulled away
Now, brother, it's been three days since he's shown himself,
and he's left her without bread, without meat,
alone in bed with two children in the cradle, and one at her breast
S: My God, what a scoundrel! And you wanted...
F: Quiet!
Just imagine how she manages nursing that poor child
"The barrel gives the wine it has," says the proverb
"To feed on anger is to drink of poison,"
sleep eludes, even with poppy's aid,
when filled with such deep sorrow and quiet pain
Oh, what a scoundrel!
You should seek justice, madam
I hope to bring him around, if possible, through reason
This rogue deserves no mercy
Ah, brother, legal disputes and courts are not for me
"Money and friendship break justice's neck,"
says the proverb...
"and he who dosen't 'grease the weal' is always wrong."
And then there are hearings, mandates, appeals, citations, contradictions, examinations, and witnesses
My dear brother, it never ends...
And I am old, and full of woes
I have a tumor in my knee
that forces me to limp
I have a fistula in this eye
that always makes me tear up
I have a cough that's killing me,
And I struggle to breathe
That poor girl...
She's on the verge of fading away
Ah, what will become of me?
If on top of so many woes, I had to face litigation
I have a tumor in my knee
that forces me to limp
Che ne dite ?
What do you think?
Ah, my child, I've nearly lost my mind
If Nencio has a wife, he can't marry me?
We'll send him to marry the pillory
Scoundrel! Rogue! Woe to him if he comes before me
Yet you say he's rich...?
Oh, perhaps riches are a privilege for those with wicked inclinations to become scoundrels
So, it's better to be poor?
Certainly
Better to be miserable than wicked
Ah, if the devil brings him to me again, I don't know what I'll do with that unworthy
S: There he is!
F: We'd better avoid the confrontation
Hey Filippo! Sandrina! Don't shut the door, listen!
What's the meaning of this fine courtesy?
They surely saw me and know the reason I'm tracking them down,
and yet they slam the door in my face like this
I want to know what's going on
Is no one answering?
Hey, anyone home?
Really? By Bacchus!
Chi è ?
Who is it?
It's me, Filippo. It's Nencio.
Open up, don't you recognize me?
Figures, were you deaf? [REVISIT]
And what do you want?
Oh, really? What do I want?
I've done everything. I've found the notary
I've invited the relatives and if you want, the wedding can be held tonight
You can go marry a galley
Rogue, scoundrel,
Accursed rascal!
Go to your wife,
Go feed your children
Unworthy!
Get out of my sight, or taste this rod
You would marry Sandrina?
Get that thought out of your head
Either the gallows or the pillory, perhaps one day, will marry you
Never come before me again, true scum of scoundrels
Full of vices and sins
without love, nor charity
You would marry Sandrina?
People are murmering,
The miserable wife begs for mercy
The unfortunate abandoned has no aid,
She has no bread
Never come before me again, true scum of scoundrels
without love, nor charity
Countryman!
Who is this?
[Invented words]
No answer?
Sir, I don't understand
I speak 'Italiano'
Yes, speak 'Christiano' and then I'll understand you
Where is my master?
And how would I know?
He come to marry [invented words] Filippo
I stop at [invented words] and not find
Can you teach me?
I don't understand even a single word
V: Ah, is he drunk?
N: Bravo! That's the way to put it
I had recognizing your face
From with me, we go back to the pub?
Yeah right, I have other intentions
Ah, scoundrel. Drank too much?
This fiasco is just what I needed
Take this [made-up words]
Sir don't inconvenience yourserlf
[made-up words] don't want
What is this nonsense?
Me want, take bottle on head
Please dont; I'll drink
Ah, [made-up words] countryman
When master Sandrina have married,
want get drunk, want give [made-up words] in company,
want dance and be in joy
What? Your master is to marry Sandrina?
Yes, pretty [made-up word]
And the wedding is today?
[Made-up words]
[made-up words] joyfully
That master today marry
You dance, you sing
I want get drunk
[made-up words] countryman
[made-up words] not pay anything
Everything is now clear to me
Now I understand Filippo's departure
He has found a better match
And to not appear as a turncoat or crazy,
he made up that excuse and harrasses me
But I will set things right
I no longer care about that foolish girl
For me, it's over, but I want to at least tell her bluntly my side of the story
To show her that I can sing as well
I don't care about that gossip
But I don't want to be painted as ridiculous
I want things to proceed orderly
I don't want to be dominated
I'm not worried. There's no real danger in returning to argue with old men
But I want to talk. I want to vent
At least I will make him learn how to bargain
Gentleman
Most Illustrious
What are you doing?
Nothing, sir
What do you mean nothing? What do you seek from that house?
I was going to speak a word to Filippo
Do you know him?
Of course
And me?
I don't believe I've ever seen you before
Listen here, you clod, and you will know
I am the Marquis of Ripafratta,
who has fiefs, and marquisates, baronies, and principalities,
and who, by the hundreds in nobility,
counts the quarters and measures them by the bushel
Ah, I believe it, Most Illustrious One
That's not all
Know that in my service I have pages, and I have knights, lackys, stable boys, and black capes,
and a world full of beasts and persons,
And that if you ever dare approach this door again...
I will have you beaten to death under a cane
Ah Sir, please don't inconvenience yourself!
Did you understand?
Ah, Most Illustrious, yes
Watch your back
Undoubtedly
But know that Filippo dealt me a nasty slight
What then?
Last night, just last night, he promised me Sandrina's hand
I came this morning to marry her as agreed,
And he chased me away, like a whipped dog
Ah, ah, you make me laugh
Eh, I know that Sandrina is getting married to you today
But I'd like to get even with him
With whom?
With that old man
And you think our marriage is all settled?
Oh, unfortunately, I know
Poor fool. Do you think I'd degrade my many titles, and such lofty and supreme nobility, to marry a mere peasant?
But a certain German servant of yours...
He believes it, and so does Filippo
In fact, for Sandrina I do feel love, so to give her great honor, I'll marry her to my kitchen boy
When drafting the contract, the names will be changed
And one of my servants will step in for the marriage
And she will be a maid at my service
Oh, wonderful! But once Filippo finds out, what will he say?
What do you want him to say?
Sandrina agrees, and once the contract is signed, there's no remedy, and what's done is done
He's going to look so foolish
Oh, how much I'd pay to be present at this wedding!
Come, you can serve as a witness
Ah, please do it, sir, for pity's sake!
Where do you live?
Over there
Go there and wait
I'll send a servant to notify you
I'll go
Oh, what delight!
If I get to see this old man foaming at the mouth, raging, fuming...
The marchioness, the cook, when it's finally revealed...
What yelling, that ashen face
What will that old wizard do?
I believe I'll die of laughter, that I'll burst
Let's spread out this table cloth here
Here, a chair. Here another. A stool. One more here
Alright
Oh my dear, you were born with a silver spoon in your mouth
Indeed, a great fortune!
Oh silly girl. Look at you! You're about to become a great lady
And lose the habit of working and staying healthy
Always traveling by carriage or by palanquin
When one has such good legs, it would feel like being in the pillory
Always dress in fine cloth and velvet
And perhaps suffer more the cold
Have the pleasure of always wearing a pannier
Oh surely, the joy isn't small of banging one's shins in that contraption
Have many persons at your service
And let the public know all one's private business
Have not just a meal on the table every day - but a feast
A great invention, intended to erase one's appetite
Shut it silly girl, or else I'll hit you
But how do you expect me to adapt to becoming a great lady?
What? Do you believe you are the first? Oh my daughter, when fortune provides the rest,
arrogance and folly make their nest
But hush. I hear people
Might it be the Marquis returning with the notary to draft the contract?
Very soon, you'll see what a change of clothes can mean
Oh no! Give me simple bread and onions, and my dear Nanni
Pomp is a great deception
Per un'anima che disprezza il fasto, l'onor, e la ricchezza
For a soul that scorns ostentation, honor, and wealth
I seek not, and I do not desire,
but the peace of my heart
At your most illustrious service
To whom do you speak?
With you, don't you see?
My master has sent me here with the notary
to draft his marriage contract
And he told me to bring a witness
Oh wonderful, how delightful!
And the Marquis?
Shouldn't he be present for this?
He will come to sign the contract
He has now gone to make arrangements for the departure, the dresses for the bride, the ceremonial carriages, and everything besides
Ah, my dear daughter, what great fortune is this?
Indeed, Mr. Notary, I would suggest you begin to write
I'm ready
In the year 1700, with a public instrument, those present and accepting, willing and consenting,
the following are to be wed
Who knows the names?
The daughter's name is Sandra of Mugnone
And the master's name?
The servant will tell you
He's a Count, and he's a Baron
He's a  Prince, and he's a Marquis
We shall soon see
What is the dowry?
This is a poor girl, who has nothing and is marrying for charity
Nothing as a dowry
nor as a trousseau
So I believe
So it is known
Così promettono, così si sposano
Thusly they vow, thusly they wed
not constraining and obligating themselves
This will suffice
Let them sign
Where?
Right here the witnesses
Here they are
Where is the Marquis?
Where is the groom?
He's arriving now
(It makes me laugh in truth)
But when is he coming?
Here he is
This is my Nanni
This is Vespina
Mi vien da ridere, in verità
It makes me laugh in truth
Che baronata! Che imbroglio è questo?
What a farce! What is this deception?
Thus infidelity is punished
I won't agree to any pact
I know well what I will do
The contract is made and signed, it can no longer be undone
You are my wife
you are my husband
This is finished, and, as so, how it goes
Mister errant one, mister vagabond, leave here at once
Nobody has pity for me in the world
What will become of me?
Listen, scoundrel
You do me great wrong
The wife betrayed
A stale lie
The children abandoned
Inventied slander
Listen! Be quiet!
Now you will actually see what has happened
I pretended to be the old woman who speaks in proverbs
The German servant [invented words]
Enough, it was you, Vespina, with such an uncouth manner
You knew how to trick us
Heaven give me patience
it's is an insolence
But what does one do?
What's done is done
So let us then be cheeful
that in a double wedding today at least we will rejoice
[Applause]
Subtitles by Michael Jurado